[HOLMES] MP Whiteley, murdered
by the Lord of Crime.
[HOLMES]
There's more at play here.
Yes, Miss Hudson?
What's the matter?
[HUDSON giggles]
John? Who's this?
May I present Miss Mary Morstan.
Currently, she's employed
for Misses Forrester,
serving as a governess.
I'm a little late
in announcing this, but
you see, we're getting married.
[HOLMES]
Uh.
Misses Forrester, you said?
The same one I consulted
two months ago?
Right.
After the case, she invited
the both of us to dinner.
I was the only taker.
Good thing. That was
where I met Mary.
Yes. If I may be honest,
Misses Forrester was
disappointed
you weren't able to attend.
But she understands you
are a rather busy man.
[WATSON] Even so, I'm
glad I didn't miss it.
[WATSON] We might have
never run into each other.
[HOLMES]
What else?
Clearly there's another matter
besides your wedding
that you came to bother me with.
[GROUP grunts]
How rude! Do you just blurt out
whatever thought
enters your head?
Come now, she's nervous
enough without you--
[MARY]
John. [grunts]
Mister Holmes is correct.
[WATSON grunts]
Now, however,
I feel as though it'll sound
like a rather brazen request.
Please proceed.
[MARY] If you would
kindly have a look at these.
Astounding! I've never laid eyes
on pearls as large as those!
Judging from the size,
you could live for half a year
by the sale of a single one.
[MARY] These pearls started
arriving out of the blue,
once per year, and each
one on the same day,
starting about six years ago.
The sender's name isn't
provided on the postage slip.
Take me through
the order of events.
Of course. But to do so,
I must begin by telling you
all about my dearest father.
[MARY]
He was a soldier.
An officer who
was posted to India.
My mother passed away
when I was young,
so I was taken in by a girls'
boarding school while he served.
Then, ten years ago,
my father sent me a telegram.
He was home on leave and
asked me to come to his hotel.
I was excited to
see his face again,
but when I arrived,
his room--
It was completely empty
save for his luggage.
And to this day, I'm afraid
that his whereabouts
remain a complete mystery to me.
His disappearance and
the arrival of the pearls.
What do you believe
is their connection?
Not very long ago,
I learned about my
father's time during the war.
While stationed in India,
he became close to a Major
Sholto from his regiment .
I thought perhaps he
might know something,
but after looking
up his address,
I learnt that he had passed away
six years ago, unfortunately.
I see.
Right around the same
time these pearls
first began
arriving in the mail.
Which is why you believe
the two events are related.
[MARY]
Mm.
Mister Holmes, I beg of you.
I wish to know what
has become of my father.
Would you please lend
me your assistance?
[HOLMES] I will give it
my undivided attention.
Do forgive me, John.
I didn't mean to spring
this on you so suddenly.
No worries.
Rest assured, Sherlock and I
will unravel this mystery.
Thank you, John.
Miss Morstan--what
a charming young lady.
[HOLMES] You think so?
I didn't particularly notice.
[HUDSON gasps]
You're joking.
You mean the master of detection
couldn't see what was right
in front of his nose?
[HOLMES] To be fair,
she wasn't forthright.
[gasps]
I don't know what it is yet,
but she's holding
something back.
[MARY]
Pondicherry Lodge?
Major Sholto's estate.
A vast property
purchased 11 years ago
after completing his
service in India.
Apparently, he retired.
Thanks to his business
dealings overseas,
the major returned a rich man
along with a menagerie
of rare curosities.
But no matter how
hard I searched,
I wasn't able to find any record
of him doing business in India.
Once home, it's said he lived
an extravagant lifestyle,
But strangely,
became deathly afraid
of going out in public alone.
[gun fires]
[HOLMES] Also of note,
there was an incident
where he mistakenly fired
a gun at a merchant,
a man with a wooden leg.
But why on earth
would he do that?
That's odd.
[gasps]
[HOLMES]
John! Quickly!
[WATSON panting] What the
devil is it, Sherlock?
We're intruding!
[HOLMES]
You in there! Are you all right?
Damn!
[HOLMES gasps]
What? My word!
[HOLMES] This is finally
shaping up to be a case.
[WATSON]
He's dead. Who is he?
He's one of Major
Sholto's twin sons.
Either Thaddeus or Bartholomew.
[HOLMES] Cleary a victim of
homicide. Have a look, John.
[WATSON gasps] What is that?
Looks like a thorn.
A poison barb, it seems.
Definitely not from England.
[HOLMES sniffs]
[MARY yelps]
[THADDEUS]
Who's there?
[gasps]
No, it can't be. Are you...
...Miss Mary Morstan?
[gasps]
[THADDEUS] But what are
you doing in our mansion?
[THADDEUS gasping]
[THADDEUS]
Bartholomew!
[gasps] My dear brother!
What's happened to you?
[HOLMES]
You must be the other twin.
Thaddeus, right?
I need you to shed
light on a few matters:
Where Mary's father is,
the pearls that are
being sent to her,
as well as your brother's death.
[THADDEUS grunts]
[gun fires]
[THADDEUS]
After the shooting incident,
my father rarely
ventured in public again.
Then six years ago,
outside, drawn on
the mansion's gate
were four mysterious symbols.
My father nearly collapsed.
Afterward, he became bedridden,
and finally told us
his confession.
Oh, my word.
[SHOLTO]
The Treasure of Agra.
Or to be more precise,
one small piece of it.
See, I did not obtain my fortune
through business ventures.
It was sheer luck.
My subordinate Morstan and I
came upon it quite unexpectedly.
I resigned my post immediately
and brought the treasure
back to England.
It was about a year later,
Morstan also returned
and arrived at my door.
However, the reunion was short
lived, a quarrel broke out.
How we should
divide the treasure.
[inaudible]
[SHOLTO]
Whereupon...
If only I had called a doctor,
my comrade may have survived.
Alas.
Promise me, you will give
what remains of the treasure
to Morstan's only daughter,
Mary.
You'll find it hidden
in the mansion's--
[screaming]
[SHOLTO]
I-It's him! He's come for me!
Drive that fiend away at once!
[THADDEUS]
I dashed over to the window.
But there was no one there.
When I turned around,
my father had already
taken his last breath.
After his passing,
my brother and I
searched for the treasure.
But to no avail.
So I started sending her
whatever I could,
one pearl each year.
So that's what happened.
I'm sorry, Mary, truly.
So it exists after all.
[HOLMES]
Hm?
The Treasure of Agra.
We believed it to be lost.
Then my brother discovered
the chest just the other day.
How did everything go so wrong?
After our father passed,
we found this in the safe.
[HOLMES] The paper is Indian
and displays some sort of map,
accompanied by a row
of four blood seals.
Jonathan Small, Abdullah Tonga,
John Sholto, and Arthur Morstan.
Small and Tonga--who are they?
[THADDEUS]
I do not know.
Thaddeus.
Go to the police and tell them
all that has transpired.
Uh, right.
Now then, if we proceed
beyond this point,
there is no turning back.
There's no turning back?
What do you mean?
First Major Sholto was
terrified of someone.
Then, his son,
Bartholomew, is murdered.
The evidence
indicates another party
interested in the treasure.
Someone who will go to
any lengths to obtain it.
From here on out, we cannot
guarantee Miss Morstan's safety.
I believe now's the time
for us to withdraw.
Not to mention
our original design
was never to
obtain the treasure.
[MARY grunts]
You're right. I refuse to
expose Mary to any danger.
While I'm curious
who the culprit is,
we have learnt about her
father's fate and the treasure.
Let the police handle the rest.
We should return home.
[MARY gulps]
We can't.
We must go on.
Given the current situation,
I am convinced suspicion
of Bartholomew's murder
will fall upon either
ourselves or Thaddeus.
[WATSON gasps]
[MARY] Not only did we
break into the mansion,
but the door to this
room was also locked.
We are the only ones
who can provide an alibi
for each other if
the police suspect us.
If we escape scrutiny,
no doubt Thaddeus will become
the primary suspect instead.
For his sake and our own,
I think we should
find the real culprit.
[HOLMES]
And there we have it.
On the surface, she wishes
to lend a helping hand,
but is her true intent to
recover the stolen riches
in the course of
catching the culprit?
From the very start, Mary's
objective has been the treasure.
To be more precise, a fortune
purloined during war.
It's possible she already
has plans how to spend it.
If that's the case,
it's extremely
likely she's involved
in some manner of heinous crime.
If she attempts to conceal it
before marrying John,
I'll have no choice,
but to expose her,
and reveal the truth...
...for John's sake.
So, in other words, all that's
needed is proving a third party
was in this room
before any of us.
Bob's your uncle.
[BOTH gasp]
First, Bartholomew was killed by
a pair of criminals
working together.
Earlier, I observed the ground
directly beneath the room.
One set of footprints
had a circular indentation
that was rather distinct.
Made from a wooden leg, no
doubt. Sholto's tormentor.
Then, there's the
windowsill mark
from where a rope
rubbed the ledge.
Judging by the footprints
left in the room,
the second man was smaller,
light on his feet.
He would've been able to clamber
up to the window and slip in,
then lower the chest from
the room to the ground below
where the one-legged
man was waiting.
Based on all the evidence,
it's very clear someone
else was responsible.
Is there a chance the culprits
are Small and Tonga--
the remaining pair of
the four signatories?
Do you know them?
[MARY] My father was
the officer in command
of a local battalion in India.
If I had to surmise,
Small and Tonga most likely
both served under his command.
Those blood seals may have
been forged as a contract.
[WATSON] Meaning Major Sholto
feared they would take revenge--
retaliation for keeping
the treasure all to himself.
[MARY]
Mister Holmes,
how do we go about
finding these villains?
That's remarkably simple.
[WATSON, MARY grunt]
[HOLMES] When the smaller
man was lowering the chest,
he accidentally broke
a bottle of creosol.
A powerful scent that
does not easily wash out.
[HOLMES]
The expert has arrived.
With his amazing power of scent,
he's served as a consultant
on many a case, Toby.
Well done, came
through in a pinch.
You could make it up to me.
An after-hours bonus
plus one if he finds your man.
Are you having a laugh?
Mary, dear. Would you
take the carriage Wiggins
brought with him and
wait for us at Baker Street?
Please do.
Tracking down the culprits
and the treasure is
a task best left to us.
I'll do as you ask,
but promise me
you'll be careful.
[WATSON]
Mm.
Right then, the hunt is on!
Toby, come along!
[TOBY barks]
[MARY grunts]
[WATSON]
I made some coffee.
Care for some?
Gladly, thanks.
Seen any activity
on the boat yet?
[HOLMES] The coffee isn't
the only thing steaming.
They're preparing to launch.
Small should be arriving soon.
He's bound to make his escape.
And when he does,
we'll pursue and capture him.
Why go through the trouble
of chasing the boat?
We could easily end
this by arresting them
before they depart.
We wouldn't be able to
keep Mary safe if we did.
[WATSON grunts]
What do you mean?
Small may not have
murdered Bartholomew,
but the burglary may prove
to be a rather unique challenge.
After getting out of
jail in a few years,
if the treasure is
in Mary's possession,
he will surely come
to claim it from her.
[gasps]
There's one way for us to
prevent any future reprisals.
We need Small to abandon all
claim he has to the treasure.
How can we force him to--
[engine sputters]
[HOLMES]
Speak of the devil!
Wooden-leg, 12 o' clock.
May I present, Small!
Look alive, you lot!
Lestrade! Get after that launch!
And you're absolutely certain
there's a murderer
aboard the boat, right?
[HOLMES]
For the thousandth time, yes!
Hurry!
Douse the lights so
they don't see us coming!
By Jove, put yourself
in my shoes--
taking a Yard police-boat
without permission like this!
C'mon, get us moving!
[WATSON]
Distance, about 50 yards.
[HOLMES]
All right.
This should be plenty deep
enough. Hit the lights!
Huh?
[HOLMES]
Ahoy, Jonathan Small!
Abdullah Tonga!
We're well aware of your
nefarious deeds, sirs!
Hand over the Treasure of Agra,
and answer for
killing Bartholomew!
But how?
We didn't leave a single
bloody witness behind.
[CAPTAIN 21A gasps]
I knew there was something
crooked about you two blokes!
Watch your tongue!
I paid you a tidy sum!
You're an accomplice now!
So if you wish to
keep breathin',
I suggest you lose 'em.
[CAPTAIN 21A whimpers]
[HOLMES] Stop the boat
and hand over the treasure,
nice and easy!
Fool! Don't be so dumb!
A pact was made!
The treasure is rightfully ours!
[SMALL, CAPTAIN 21A gasp]
[WATSON]
Sherlock!
[HOLMES] Stop the boat
if you want to live!
He's mad!
The thief means
to take our fortune,
even if it requires shooting us!
What are you doing?
[WATSON gasps]
[WATSON]
Sherlock! Watch out!
[gun firing]
[groans]
They shot him!
It's all gone to hell!
Captain! Can't this
rubbish heap move faster?!
I already pushed her too hard!
The boiler is going to explode!
[SMALL]
No. Damn it.
Damn it all!
It's not yours! The treasure,
it's mine! All mine!
You won't take it!
I won't let you!
No one's getting their
hands on what belongs to me!
[thud]
[HOLMES, WATSON gasp]
[SMALL cackling]
If you blokes still
want my treasure,
it belongs to the Thames now.
[SMALL cackling]
[WATSON]
Huh. That's how...
[HOLMES]
Indeed.
Thanks to this spectacle,
Small has voluntarily given up
his claim to the fortune.
[SMALL cackling]
On the whole, Small's
testimony was nearly identical
to what you and
Sherlock deduced.
[MARY] I'm relieved you
caught the criminals
without incident.
[MARY]
So then, where's the treasure?
[WATSON]
Mary, the thing of it is...
I'm afraid it all
went overboard.
[gasps]
[HOLMES] Rather than having
it fall into another's hands,
he let the Thames claim it.
It... was lost?
For the best. If you had it
in your possession then,
those two scoundrels would
come after you, looking for it.
We have each other; that's
the only treasure we need.
[MARY]
But without it, he's going to...
[HOLMES] I did detect a sort of
desperation in your behaviour.
You wanted your
hands on that gold.
When you heard about the
existence of the treasure
from Thaddeus, you did not
seem overly surprised.
Which means, you knew
about it beforehand,
but hid the fact from us.
Even after a murder
had been committed,
you put recovering the fortune
above your own personal safety.
Which might strike some as odd,
seeing as you are employed
and haven't sold any of the
pearls that were sent to you.
That tells me, you are not short
or in desperate need of cash.
Once that's excluded, then
only one possibility remains.
Blackmail.
[MARY gasps]
Then, I'm right.
[WATSON]
Now, just a moment!
Is that true? Mary,
who would blackmail you?
[MARY whimpers] If I didn't
turn over the treasure,
he said I would pay.
That he'd break up our wedding.
[WATSON grunts]
Tell me the name of this devil!
Who would dare stoop
to such a vile act?
Only one name comes to mind.
The king of blackmailers,
Charles Augustus Milverton.
Evil personified.
[WILLIAM] Next time on
Moriarty the Patriot  :
"The Two Criminals."